<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../xsl/command.xsl"?>
<command xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../xsd/command.xsd">
  <name>re_trigger_options</name>
  <description>changes options for a corresponding trigger</description>
  <syntax>re_trigger_options rt_name option_list</syntax>
  <arguments>
    <argument>
      <name>mask</name>
      <description>value represents a bit mask which determines which types of messages can cause activation of a trigger:
1 - pickup messages 
2 - death messages 
4 - critical messages (most of TeamFortress messages) 
8 - chat 
16 - centerprint 
32 - echo command output 
64 - other strings printed in the console
The default mask for any trigger equals 31.</description>
    </argument>
    <argument>
      <name>interval</name>
      <description>sets a minimal interval of trigger activation (in seconds). If a second activation happened earlier than the value time - it is ignored. Default is 0.</description>
    </argument>
    <argument>
      <name>final</name>
      <description>if activation of this trigger happened, the remaining (in the list of triggers) triggers are not 
checked. Triggers are checked in a reversed order of their definition.</description>
    </argument>
    <argument>
      <name>notfinal</name>
      <description>activation of such trigger doesn't stop the checking of other triggers (default).</description>
    </argument>
    <argument>
      <name>remove</name>
      <description>a string which caused activation of a trigger is not printed on the screen.</description>
    </argument>
    <argument>
      <name>noremove</name>
      <description>a string which caused activation of a trigger is printed on the screen (default).</description>
    </argument>
    <argument>
      <name>log</name>
      <description>a string which caused activation of a trigger is not added to a log-file.</description>
    </argument>
    <argument>
      <name>nolog</name>
      <description>a string which caused activation of a trigger is added to a log-file (default).</description>
    </argument>
    <argument>
      <name>noaction</name>
      <description>a corresponding alias is not executed upon a trigger activation. There is no need to exec alias if all you need is to use remove option :)</description>
    </argument>
    <argument>
      <name>action</name>
      <description>a corresponding alias is executed upon a trigger activation (default).</description>
    </argument>
  </arguments>
  <remarks>enable	allows activation of a trigger (default).	
disable	prohibits activation of a trigger.

Triggers would not work for debugging messages like snd_show 1. In Team Fortress triggers would not work for commands showloc and id (of enemy), and for message of your dispencer being used by enemies.</remarks>
</command>
